Contagious is a good word.
العدوى كلمة جيدة.
Even in the times of H1N1, I like the word.
حتى في وقت " انفلونزا الخنازير" H1N1,انا احب هذه الكلمة.
Laughter is contagious. Passion is contagious.
الضحك عدوى. العاطفة عدوى.
Inspiration is contagious.
الالهام عدوى.
We've heard some remarkable stories from some remarkable speakers.
سبق وسمعنا قصص جديرة بالملاحظة من بعض المتحدثين الجديرين بالملاحظة.
But for me, what was contagious about all of them
لكن بالنسبة لي, مالذي نقل العدوى لهم جميعاً
was that they were infected by something I call the
هل نقلت العدوى لهم عن طريق شيء انا اسميه
"I Can" bug.
جرثومة "انا استطيع".
So, the question is, why only them?
اذاً, السؤال هو, لماذا فقط هم؟
In a country of a billion people and some,
في بلد البليون نسمة واكثر,
why so few?
لماذا فقط القليل؟
Is it luck? Is it chance?
هل هو الحظ؟ هل هي الفرصة؟
Can we all not systematically and consciously
هل يمكننا جميعا بطريقة غير منهجية وبدون ادراك
get infected?
ان تُنقل لنا العدوى؟
So, in the next eight minutes I would like to share with you my story.
اذاً, في الدقائق الثمان التالية اريد ان اشارككم قصتي.
I got infected when I was 17,
انتقلت لي العدوى عندما كنت في السابعة عشر,
when, as a student of the design college,
عندما, كطالبة في كلية التصميم
I encountered adults who actually believed in my ideas,
انا قابلت "انداز", الذي يؤمن فعلا بأفكاري,
challenged me and had lots of cups of chai with me.
تحداني, وشرب معي الكثير من أكواب الشاي.
And I was struck by just how wonderful it felt,
وشعرت بالذهول من هذا الاحساس الرائع
and how contagious that feeling was.
وكيف كانت عدوى ذلك الاحساس .
I also realized I should have got infected when I was seven.
انا ايضاً ادركت بأني كنت يجب ان اتلقى العدوى عندما كنت في السابعة
So, when I started Riverside school 10 years ago it became a lab,
اذاً, عندما انشأت مدرسة "ريفرسايد" قبل عشر سنوات اصبحت مختبر,
a lab to prototype and refine a design process
مختبر لنموذج و صقل عملية التصميم
that could consciously infect the mind with the "I Can" bug.
والذي يمكن ان يعدي العقل بواسطة بعوضة "انا استطيع".
And I uncovered
وانا اكتشفت,
that if learning is embedded in real-world context,
أنه اذا كان التعلم مطمور في سياق العالم الحقيقي,
that if you blur the boundaries between school and life,
انك اذا قمت بطمس الحدود بين المدرسة والحياة,
then children go through a journey of "aware,"
فإن الأطفال سيذهبون في رحلة من الادراك,
where they can see the change,
حيث يمكنهم رؤية التغيير,
"enable," be changed,
فيتغيرون,
and then "empower," lead the change.
ومن ثم يملكون القدرة على قيادة التغيير.
And that directly increased student wellbeing.
وهذا مباشرة يزيد رفاهية الطالب.
Children became more competent,
الاطفال اصبحوا اكثر كفاءة,
and less helpless.
وأقل عجزاً.
But this was all common sense.
ولكن هذا كله كان بديهياً.
So, I'd like to show you a little glimpse of what
لذا, اريد ان اريكم لمحة صغيرة عن
common practice looks like at Riverside.
كيف يبدو التدريب المشترك في "ريفرسايد".
A little background: when my grade five was learning about child rights,
خلفية بسيطة: عندما كان طلابي في الصف الخامس يتعلمون عن حقوق الطفل,
they were made to roll incense sticks,
كانوا يلفّون أعواد البخور,
agarbattis, for eight hours
لمدة ثمان ساعات
to experience what it means to be a child laborer.
ليجربوا ما معنى ان تكون طفلاً عاملاً.
It transformed them. What you will see is their journey,
لقد تحولوا. ما سترونه هو رحلتهم,
and then their utter conviction
وثم اقتناعهم التام
that they could go out and change the world.
بأنهم سيخرجوا و يغيروا العالم.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
That's them rolling.
هاهم يلفّون.
And in two hours, after their backs were broke,
و خلال ساعتين, بعد ان كُسرت ظهورهم,
they were changed.
كانوا قد تغيروا.
And once that happened,
وعندما يحدث هذا,
they were out in the city convincing everybody
يكونون خارجاً في المدينة يقنعون الجميع
that child labor just had to be abolished.
ان ظاهرة عمل الأطفال يجب ان تلغى.
And look at Ragav, that moment when his face changes
و انظروا الى "راجاف", تلك اللحظة التي تغير فيها وجهه
because he's been able to understand that he
لأنه كان قادراً على فهم أنه
has shifted that man's mindset.
غيّر عقلية هذا الرجل.
And that can't happen in a classroom.
وهذا لم يكن ليحدث في الصف.
So, when Ragav experienced that
اذاً, عندما جرّب "راجاف" انه
he went from "teacher told me,"
ذهب من "المعلم قال لي,"
to "I am doing it." And that's the "I Can" mindshift.
الى "أنا أعمله." وهذا "أنا أستطيع" تغيير العقل.
And it is a process that can be energized and nurtured.
وهي عملية يمكن تنشيطها و تنميتها.
But we had parents who said,
ولكن لدينا آباء يقولون,
"Okay, making our children good human beings is all very well,
"حسناً, جعل أطفالنا بشرا ًجيدين حسنٌ جداً,
but what about math and science and English?
ولكن ماذا عن الرياضيات والعلوم واللغة الانجليزية؟
Show us the grades."
أرونا العلامات."
And we did. The data was conclusive.
ففعلنا. المعلومات كانت مقنعة.
When children are empowered,
عندما يتم تمكين الاطفال,
not only do they do good,
ليسوا فقط يؤدون بشكل جيد,
they do well, in fact very well,
بل يؤدون بشكل ممتاز, بل ممتاز جداً,
as you can see in this national benchmarking assessment
وكما ترون في هذا التقييم الوطني المعياري
taken by over 2,000 schools in India,
والذي شمل اكثر من ألفي مدرسة في الهند,
Riverside children were outperforming the top 10 schools in India
أطفال ريفرسايد تفوقوا على افضل عشر مدارس في الهند
in math, English and science.
في الرياضيات, الإنجليزية و العلوم.
So, it worked. It was now time to take it outside Riverside.
اذاً, انها ناجحة. فقد حان الوقت الآن لأخذها خارج الريفرسايد.
So, on August 15th, Independence Day, 2007,
اذاً, في الخامس عشر من أغسطس, يوم التحرير, 2007,
the children of Riverside set out to infect Ahmedabad.
أطفال الريفرسايد هم أساس نقل العدوى في أحمدأباد.
Now it was not about Riverside school.
الآن الأمر ليس عن مدرسة ريفرسايد.
It was about all children. So, we were shameless.
بل عن جميع الأطفال. لذلك كنا قليلوا الحياء.
We walked into the offices of the municipal corporation, the police,
لقد دخلنا في مكاتب المؤسسة البلدية, والشرطة,
the press, businesses,
الصحافة, والأعمال التجارية.
and basically said, "When are you going to wake up
واساساً قلنا, "متى سوف تستيقظون
and recognize the potential that resides in every child?
وتدركون الإمكانية التي تسكن كل طفل.
When will you include the child in the city?
متى سوف تضمون الطفل الى المدينة؟
Basically, open your hearts and your minds to the child."
أساساً, افتحوا قلوبكم وعقولكم للطفل."
So, how did the city respond?
اذاً, كيف أجابت المدينة؟
Since 2007 every other month
منذ 2007 في كل شهرين
the city closes down the busiest streets for traffic
تغلق المدينة الشوارع المزدحمة لحركة المرور
and converts it into a playground for children and childhood.
وتحولها الى ملعب للأطفال والطفولة.
Here was a city telling its child, "You can."
هنا كانت مدينة تحدث طفلها," أنت تستطيع."
A glimpse of infection in Ahmedabad.
لمحة من حالات العدوى في أحمدأباد.
Video: [Unclear]
فيديو:(غير واضح)
So, the busiest streets closed down.
اذاً, الشوارع المزدحمة أُغلقت.
We have the traffic police and municipal corporation helping us.
لدينا شرطة المرور والمجالس البلدية يساعدوننا.
It gets taken over by children.
يبدأ الإستيلاء عليها من قبل الأطفال.
They are skating. They are doing street plays.
انهم يتزلجون. ويلعبون ألعاب الشارع.
They are playing, all free, for all children.
إنهم يلعبون, بكل حرية, لجميع الأطفال.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Atul Karwal: aProCh is an organization which has been doing things for kids earlier.
أتول كاروال: Aproch هي منظمة قامت بعمل أشياء للأطفال سابقاً.
And we plan to extend this to other parts of the city.
ونحن نخطط لمد هذا الى اجزاء أخرى من المدينة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Kiran Bir Sethi: And the city will give free time.
كيران بير سيثي: والمدينة سيقدمون وقت فراغ.
And Ahmedabad got the first child-friendly zebra crossing in the world.
وأحمدأباد حصلت على أول معبر مشاة من صنع الأطفال في العالم.
Geet Sethi: When a city gives to the children,
جيت سيثي:عندما تُعطي مدينة للأطفال
in the future the children will give back to the city.
ففي المستقبل الأطفال سيعطون المدينة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
KBS: And because of that,
kbs:ولهذا السبب,
Ahmedabad is known as India's first child-friendly city.
أحمدأباد تُعرف كأول مدينة صديقة للطفولة في الهند.
So, you're getting the pattern. First 200 children at Riverside.
اذاً,فهمتم الفكرة .أول 200 طفل في ريفرسايد.
Then 30,000 children in Ahmedabad, and growing.
ثم 30,000 طفل في أحمدأباد, ويزيد العدد.
It was time now to infect India.
لقد حان الوقت الآن لنقل العدوى للهند.
So, on August 15th,
اذاً, في الخامس عشر من أغسطس,
again, Independence Day, 2009,
مرة أخرى, يوم التحرير, 2009,
empowered with the same process,
القدرة مع نفس العملية,
we empowered 100,000 children to say, "I can."
لقد منحنا القدرة ل 100,000 طفل ليقولوا, "أنا أستطيع."
How? We designed a simple toolkit,
كيف؟ قمنا بتصميم أدوات بسيطة,
converted it into eight languages,
و حولناها الى ثمان لغات,
and reached 32,000 schools.
ووصلنا الى 32,000 مدرسة.
We basically gave children a very simple challenge.
نحن أساساً أعطينا الأطفال تحدٍ في غاية البساطة.
We said, take one idea,
قلنا, خذوا فكرة واحدة,
anything that bothers you,
أي شي يزعجكم,
choose one week,
اختاروا اسبوعاً واحداً,
and change a billion lives.
و غيروا بليون حياة.
And they did. Stories of change
ففعلوا.قصص التغيير
poured in from all over India,
تدفقت من كل أنحاء الهند,
from Nagaland in the east,
من نجالاند في الشرق,
to Jhunjhunu in the west,
الى جونجون في الغرب,
from Sikkim in the north, to Krishnagiri in the south.
ومن سيكيم في الشمال, الى كرشناجري في الجنوب.
Children were designing solutions for a diverse range of problems.
الأطفال كانوا يصممون الحلول لمجموعة متنوعة من المشاكل.
Right from loneliness to filling potholes in the street
مباشرة من الوحدة الى ردم الحفر في الشارع,
to alcoholism,
لإدمان الكحول,
and 32 children who stopped 16 child marriages
و 32 طفل اوقفوا 16 من زواجات الأطفال
in Rajasthan.
في راجاستان.
I mean, it was incredible.
اعني, لقد كان رائعاً.
Basically again reaffirming that when adults believe in children
أساساً مرة أخرى للتأكيد أن الكبار إذا آمنوا بالأطفال
and say, "You can," then they will.
وقالوا, "أنتم تستطيعون," فسوف يستطيعون.
Infection in India.
نقل العدوى في الهند.
This is in Rajasthan, a rural village.
هذا في راجاستان, قرية ريفية.
Child: Our parents are illiterate and we want to teach them how to read and write.
طفل: أبآونا أميون ونحن نريد أن نعلمهم القراءة والكتابة.
KBS: First time, a rally and a street play in a rural school --
KBS:أول مرة, تجمع ولعب في الشوارع في مدرسة ريفية --
unheard of -- to tell their parents why literacy is important.
لم يُسمع بها -- ليخبر والديهم لماذا تعلم القراءة والكتابة مهم.
Look at what their parents says.
انظروا ماذا قال والديهم.
Man: This program is wonderful.
رجل:هذا البرنامج رائع.
We feel so nice that our children can teach us how to read and write.
نشعر بإحساس جميل أن ابناءنا يستطيعون تعليمنا القراءة والكتابة.
Woman: I am so happy that my students did this campaign.
امراءة:أنا سعيدة جداً أن تلاميذي قاموا بهذه الحملة.
In the future, I will never doubt my students' abilities.
في المستقبل, لن أشك أبداً في قدرات تلاميذي.
See? They have done it.
رأيتم؟ لقد فعلوها.
KBS: An inner city school in Hyderabad.
KBS: مدرسة داخل البلد في حيدرأباد.
Girl: 581. This house is 581 ...
فتاة:هذا البيت هو 581...
We have to start collecting from 555.
يجب أن نبدأ الجمع من 555
KBS: Girls and boys in Hyderabad, going out,
KBS: بنات وأولاد في حيدرأباد, خرجوا,
pretty difficult, but they did it.
صعب جداً, ولكنهم فعلوا.
Woman: Even though they are so young, they have done such good work.
امرأة:مع أنهم لا زالوا صغاراً, إلا أنهم قاموا بعمل جيد.
First they have cleaned the society, then it will be Hyderabad, and soon India.
أولاً قاموا بتنظيف المجتمع, ثم ستكون حيدر أباد, وقريباً الهند.
Woman: It was a revelation for me. It doesn't strike me
امراءة:لقد كانت مفاجأة مذهلة بالنسبة لي. لم يكن يبدو لي
that they had so much inside them.
أنهم يملكون الكثير بداخلهم.
Girl: Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
فتاة: شكراً سيداتي سادتي.
For our auction we have some wonderful paintings for you,
في مزادنا العلني لدينا بعض اللوحات الرائعة لكم,
for a very good cause,
لأجل سبب جيد جداً,
the money you give us will be used to buy hearing aids.
المال الذي ستعطوننا سوف يستعمل لشراء أدوات السمع.
Are you ready, ladies and gentlemen? Audience: Yes!
هل أنتم مستعدون سيداتي سادتي؟ الجمهور: نعم !
Girl: Are you ready? Audience: Yes!
فتاة: هل أنتم مستعدون؟ الجمهور: نعم !
KBS: So, the charter of compassion starts right here.
KBS:اذاً, ميثاق التراحم يبدأ من هنا.
Street plays, auctions, petitions.
مسرحيات الشارع, المزادات, الإلتماسات.
I mean, they were changing lives.
أعني, إنهم يغيرون حياة الآخرين.
It was incredible.
لقد كان رائعاً.
So, how can we still stay immune?
اذاً, كيف يمكن ان نبقى محصنين؟
How can we stay immune to that passion, that energy, that excitement?
كيف يمكن أن نبقى محصّنين عن هذه المشاعر, وهذه الطاقة, وهذه الإثارة؟
I know it's obvious,
أنا أعلم أنه واضح,
but I have to end with the most powerful symbol of change, Gandhiji.
لكن يجب أن أختم مع أقوى مثال للتغيير, غاندي.
70 years ago, it took one man
قبل 70 سنة, استطاع رجل واحد
to infect an entire nation
ليصيب أمة بأكملها
with the power of "We can."
بقوة "نحن نستطيع."
So, today who is it going to take
اذاً, اليوم من هو الشخص الذي سيقوم
to spread the infection from 100,000 children
بنقل العدوى من 100,000 طفل
to the 200 million children in India?
إلى 200 مليون طفل في الهند؟
Last I heard, the preamble still said, "We, the people of India," right?
آخر ما سمعت, والديباجة لا تزال تقول, "نحن, شعب الهند," أليس كذلك؟
So, if not us, then who?
إن لم يكن نحن فمن؟
If not now, then when?
إن لم يكن الآن فمتى؟
Like I said, contagious is a good word.
كما قلت, العدوى كلمة جيدة.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)